Nelson Dellis is one of the most
intriguing people, I know.
He was inspired to improve his memory,
after watching his grandmother's
sad decline, due to Alzheimer's.
He now holds a number of memory records,
including the US International record for
memorizing a deck of shuffled cards,
in 40.65 seconds.
The US International record for
memorizing,
the most digits in five minutes,
with 339 digits memorized.
As well as, the most names memorized,
in 15 minutes.
201 names.
He's the fourth time USA Memory Champion,
and currently ranks 26th in the world,
as a Memory Athlete.
He's also a superb mountain climber,
with two attempts on Everest,
and summits on Alaska's Mount McKinley.
Amongst, many other big
mountains around the world.
Nelson grew up in England,
France, and the United States.
He speaks both French, and
English as native languages.
He attended high school in Florida,
and went on to Major in Physics, and
Minor in Mathematics,
at the University of Miami.
He worked as a Veterinary Technician,
and then, after earning a master's
degree in Computer Science,
he worked as a software developer.
But now,
with the shift into memory expertise,
he's busy staying in mental shape for
competition, and
teaching people around the world,
how they can improve their own memories.
In fact, there is evidence,
that there are people out there,
with exceptional memory abilities,
who are not trained.
You can take part in the test that
scientists in neuroscience had developed,
to see how you stack up against Nelson,
and all the others,
who've taken the test so far.
More about that later.
Its such a pleasure to be interviewing
you, here, today, Nelson.
I have to say, I have a ton of questions,
I've always wanted to ask the memory ex,
expert.
But first, I wanna show our viewers,
just a little bit of your memory prowess.
I'm gonna read a list of 25
single digit numbers, and
let's see, if you can remember them.
>> Okay, just make sure to read
them out at like, one per second.
>> Okay.
>> Eight.
Seven.
Eight.
Four.
Two.
One.
All righty, we've got them.
>> Let me just review, in my mind.
Okay.
All right.
So, starting from the beginning.
[COUGH] It was, eight,
seven, eight, three,
seven, one, three, eight, four, four,
six, zero, four, eight, eight, six, eight,
seven, three, nine, six,
two, four two, one.
>> How did you do that?
>> This is, this is also as impressive.
I can do it backwards, if you want.
So, one two, four, two, six,
nine, three seven, eight six,
eights, eight, four, zero, six,
four, four, eight, three, one,
seven, three, eight, seven, eight.
>> Oh, my word.
I, I'm, I'm really impressed.
I wish, I could do that.
That, that's pretty amazing.
Now, I understand that you
develop this kind of expertise,
by using a memory system.
That, that your not a natural
memory expert, is that right?
>> That's right.
This is something that I taught
myself many many years ago.
Before that I just have an average memory.
And I you know, I, I trained it using
memory techniques, and a lot of practice.
And it's interesting you know,
a lot of people just assume that I have
a natural memory, or I was born with it.
So, they are always surprised to hear,
that its actually, something trained.
Were actually looking for,
other people looking for a people,
who have those natural skills.
And, the, it's, it's,
it's a point of interest to,
to see if that exists out there.
>> Well, can you tell us
a little bit about the system,
that you use to remember numbers?
How much practice do you
have to put in every day,
to keep up with this kind of system?
And it is,
is it the kind of thing that's useful,
or worthwhile for
an ordinary person to do?
>> Yeah.
So, keep in mind that I'm training for
a competition, so, I take
it to the next level of you know, I'm,
I'm, it's my profession, it's my work.
So I, I take it very seriously, and
spend hours a day, in training.
But when I started, you know,
it was just a hobby.
And I think, for the, everyday a person,
who maybe struggles with memory, you know,
they'd wanna hear that,
it's takes very limited,
not it takes a very short amount of
time to get as good at these techniques.
You don't have to spend hours,
is what I'm saying.
But there are some things
that are harder than others.
For example,
numbers requires [COUGH] a bit of prep.
Basically, the way I do it,
is I'll come up with pictures for
all these different numbers, so
that every time I see a number,
I think of something else,
that's more familiar to my brain.
So, if you were gonna learn the number
system, and you wanted to get very good at
numbers, you would have to
put in a bit of prep time.
But for the most part it's,
it's pretty easy to do these techniques.
>> I like that.
That sounds like it's something
that's doable by normal human beings.
>> Totally, yep.
>> But I'd like to shift now, to something
that I've always had a little bit of
trouble with, and
that's remembering names.
What kind of techniques do you have,
for memorizing names?
>> Yep, so that's probably,
the most common question I get.
Cuz that's probably,
the most useful every day thing is,
how do I remember the name
of someone I met or meet.
So, the idea is, well, basically,
any memory technique involves two things,
in my opinion.
One is visualization.
So turning, anything, you're trying to
memorize into a picture, a mental picture.
That's filled with associations,
that mean something to you.
Right?
To yourself.
The second thing is to attach that image,
to some location.
There are different ways you can do that.
The most common is,
is this thing called the memory palace,
where you use a familiar place like your
house, and you attach these images to a,
a bunch of different locations around
a path in this place, your house.
And the idea being
you remember your house.
So, it's easy to pick up,
where you left all these things, and
you can remember things in order, easier.
[NOISE] For names it's a bit
different because people come in, and
out of your life.
So, you don't know, where, or how, or
if you should store, a certain person.
You may not ever seem them again.
[LAUGH] So, what happens is you use
some distinguishing feature about them,
as the location to store the image for
their name.
So when I meet someone I always ask
you know, well, first I pay attention.
That's kind of the first thing.
Then, I'm focusing in on something
about their face, or body, or
their composure, and
whatever sticks out, I go with it.
That's my location.
That's my anchor.
And then, I ask for their name, and I turn
that name into, whatever it reminds me of.
It sometimes could be a friend who
has the same name, a celebrity,
a cartoon character.
It could maybe be a name
that sounds like an objects or
it just could be something It feels like,
or I break it down into smaller pieces,
and that reminds me of something.
It's it's, it's all a bit of practice.
But once you have that picture,
you can attach or
imagine it on that person's
distinguishing feature.
So that when you see them again,
they come to you, bringing that location,
and the image for
their name along with them.
>> This is really helpful for me, but
I, I have to admit my special difficulty
is in memorizing things rapidly.
For example, if I'm introduced
to five people consecutively,
I might get the name Mary,
and the name Miguel.
But by the time I've gotten through,
they've gotten through all five names,
I've forgotten the other three names.
The real problem is I'm just not a quick
thinker so by the time I come up with
some kind of memorable gimmick, I've
already missed the other couple of names.
>> Sure.
>> So, any advice for people like me?
>> Yeah, and that's common.
I mean, it's not easy to do that,
what I just said, very quickly.
I'm not even amazing at it.
If you rapid fire five to ten names at me,
I may not get all of them.
I need to take time and, and
make those images memorable.
So what I recommend in
situations like that,
because that happens a lot at parties
where someone's like, hey Joe,
this is Bob, Steve,
Agnes, whatever, right?
And it's just this quick introduction and
you're flustered and
you barely remember anything.
So, what you do is, go and
talk to these people one by one, and
don't be afraid to ask for
their name again.
I mean, if they expect you to have recall,
to retain all of those names really fast,
I mean, who, who can do that?
So, the, the key to remembering names
is also not to be embarrassed to ask,
from the beginning, though.
That's the key.
You don't want to ask for
their name, you know, after two or
three times having met them, right,
and you just keep avoiding and
saying hey, guy, or hey, madam, you know?
So it's, it's one of these things where
say you didn't catch all those names,
I would go reintroduce myself and
say like,
hi I, I, I'm sorry I didn't,
catch your name.
What is it?
And then as you kind of have a back and
forth conversation, you can in your mind
be then taking your time to come up
with this picture at your own pace.
>> I see that's very helpful.
Now sometimes there, there are people
like Bill Clinton and I mean Bill Clinton
is uncanny in his ability
to remember people's names.
Even people he hasn't
seen in like ten years,
he can instantly seem
to recall their names.
But for me, if I haven't seen
a person after say, three years,
I, I have real problems, I just can't
recall their name very quickly.
And I can't be practicing,
I've got a lot of other things to do, and
I never know who I might encounter.
So any advice for this kind of situation?
>> Yeah, you know, a person like
Bill Clinton, you know some people
just have a knack for certain things and
I think he has a knack for that.
Obviously, it's very important for
him too.
I mean, it's important for everybody but
I think especially, more so, for him.
And he's just a people person, you know,
and that, I think that helps when you.
He's the kind of person who will,
like, get to know everybody who he
meets no matter how important or not.
And that helps that's,
memory is all about paying attention and
if you spend a lot of time on one
thing you're gonna remember it better.
Now that's not to say that you're,
you don't give a, anything about
the person you meet, you know.
That you care, obviously so I do.
But we all work differently.
And what I would recommend
in those situations, and
I do this, because I'm not the best.
I have to try and make the effort.
So what I'll do is, usually, for example,
when I get business cards, you know,
I'll do the thing where I'm
memorizing everybody's name.
But, then, afterwards, I make sure to take
their business cards, review, even write
little notes on the cards themselves, just
stuff that stuck out about this person.
You know, oh, we had this
conversation about Mount Everest.
You know they were tall, had short hair.
I really like the way that he smelled, you
know, stuff that was important to you and
that comes out when you write it down,
what you remember.
And I keep a file of those and I'll go
through them every once in a while.
It's actually a fun game to me because
it reminds me of how many people I meet,
and how well I can remember them.
And it becomes this game and, and,
and that makes it a lot more fun,
and easier to remember names.
>> Memory is a key aspect of learning.
But if often seems that becoming
a memory expert involves
learning a number of
different kinds of systems.
And all of these systems
take a lot of practice.
And they're only useful for
specific types of memory.
For example, cards, or numbers, or faces.
Many of the learners in our course,
however, they wanna do things like
memorize complex equations, or
problem solving techniques.
They want to know,
they wanna remember the meaning of complex
philosophical terms or
monstrously convoluted verb conjugations.
I mean, in Russian we used to say that for
every, for
every rule there was an exception, and
for every exception there was a rule.
So what kind of advice do you have for
memorizing difficult theoretical
concepts that are outside the boundaries
of the kinds of things that
are ordinarily memorized?
>> Right so you know let me first
say that in competitions we memorize
specific things cards, numbers, names
because there, there has to be a way that
we can uniformly test everybody on
the same level every year, right?
But you can't at the same time have an
event, or have a competition that figures
out a way to test you on every possible
way to memorize every possible thing.
So the way I look at it,
the way I tell people is, you know,
we go into these competitions having
trained specifically cards, names,
numbers, and it's almost like
when you go to the gym, right?
You're training to be healthy and
fit overall.
But you go in and you, you,
you do specific exercises that do
work on a specific muscle set, right?
Like your biceps then your quads or
whatever and the goal is that, all around,
it'll prepare you to be able to be
active in any way in real life.
So, the same thing with memory is we
do all these things but it, it helps us
kind of round out our memory and allow
it to be able to memorize something like
complicated equations or, or
philosophical terms or whatever.
So for those types of things,
you know, it, it,
the memorizing process is really the same.
I know there are complex systems, but
that's if you want to get to a really high
level, and most people don't need to.
But basics are this, it's one,
come up with a picture.
So if you're looking at equations,
or philosophical, terms.
You're gonna approach it the same.
How do I turn that complicated
thing into a picture?
And by picture, you know, like I was
saying with the names it can be anything
it doesn't even have to do with
anything with what it actually is.
I mean, you could be looking at
an equation and the symbols look like
you know a seahorse and
a shovel, you know.
Doesn't matter.
The, the point is you want to turn what is
abstract and complicated Into something
that you know, and your brain
already has hard-wired in its brain.
Then afterwards you can insert meaning,
and, and understanding, and
all these things, and comprehension.
But the goal is come up with a picture.
The second thing is,
is to store it somewhere.
Use, like I was saying, a memory palace,
somewhere where you can access
this information at will.
But I think the, the, the tricky part,
especially for this complicated,
things that you're mention, mentioning,
is, is coming up with a picture.
And that takes a bit of practice,
but we're all capable of it.
We're very imaginative beings.
I think we can all come up with things,
on the fly, if we,
if we really let ourselves.
>> Well, let's switch focus a little
bit now from equations to text.
Let's say that you have a complex, or, or
simply a very long section of
text that you want to memorize.
For example, the lengthy test, text that's
involved in questions on interviews.
So, I should point out that this kind of
thing is, is especially difficult for
me when I'm a little
bit nervous on camera.
>> Yeah, with text you know,
it's difficult because there are a lot of
words, and a lot of little intricacies,
and, and filler words,
and you know, well, if you're reading
it and trying to remember it,
just generally the, the idea of
what's being said, that's okay.
You can pick out keywords and memorize
those or the general phrases or concepts.
You know, if you're memorizing a speech
word for word or a poem word for
word that's when those little
words obviously in between of,
and, or, so, those are important too.
But the two different kind of approaches,
I mean if you're just trying to memorize
a text in general to remember the points,
it just becomes what I was saying before.
Find these, maybe underlining these
key words, these key points, and
now you just reduced this text to
a list of words or groups of words.
And then that just becomes
turning those into pictures and
storing them in a memory palace.
>> I see.
So any advice for
people who are getting a little bit older?
How can they work to help to
keep up their memory skills?
>> Yeah, there's, there's a few things.
One, I, well,
I really have tried to stick to four
kind of key dimensions in brain health.
So, at this point, when,
what I like to promote is really brain
health rather than memory techniques.
Obviously, that's a part of it but I just
got into this because of my grandmother
and Alzheimer's and she had Alzheimer's.
And I wanted to improve my brain
health for the rest of my life.
So, what I do is one is keeping
my brain active so, you know, not
everybody wants to be a memory champion
but you can try to memorize things.
People give you numbers or you have
groceries to get, try to memorize it.
Don't write it down.
Learn a new skill.
You know, there's so
many things out there and
I'm sure so many people wanna try new
things, and they say, oh, I can't do it.
But try, right?
These are the things that
activate our brain and, and
really get the juices going, and
will keep you brain healthy.
Secondly, is be active,
so physical activity.
And you don't have to be weightlifting
crazy amounts or sprinting or anything,
but just being active is very good for
the brain.
Third, is being social.
So involving yourself with friends and
family and
your community is, has been shown to
be very helpful for brain health.
Not being in solitude and,
and, and a recluse is,
is helpful to be out with people.
And then finally, and
this is very important,
especially as you, we age, is diet.
The things we eat obviously impact our,
our body and our brain.
And one of the main things in this,
I suggest this to anybody cuz I do it,
every day I take about 1,000
milligrams of DHA omega three.
And it's you might be familiar,
it's what we might get if we ate salmon or
fish certain fish, fatty fish,
or fish oil pills, right?
But that's a very important
part to my diet, and
I believe that that's, those are the keys
to maintaining brain health.
And that,
that can be applied too at any age.
>> I think all of these kinds
of ideas are right in line with
the things that we've been
talking about in this course.
So do you have any last
bit of suggestion of, for
people to help help improve their
ability to learn and remember?
>> Yeah.
A few things is, you know, its,
I think when we were younger, you know,
there was always when were learning
things as kids, we were playful.
Always coming up with imaginative things.
And, you know, we looked at life very
joyfully and, and relaxed, right?
And I think that's, you lose that
obviously as you age a bit because you
have responsibilities and
you get into a job and all these things.
But that's where memory really
I think springs from is,
is our kind of child inner child you know?
And its,
its nice to explore that at times and
I think to have a good memory you
need to kind of let go and, and
explore that world a little more being
more creative and, bit silly, a bit fun.
And you'll find your memory improves.
That's one thing.
The other thing is, is, you know,
part of my mission is to try and
get, memory, and, and, and
understanding of memory and
brain health to be something of the past.
That we can all have healthy
brains in the future and
I work with this company Dart NeuroScience and they have this awesome kind of
research program where you can login and
take a little memory test.
It spans over two days but
it's very short.
And we basically its a ga,
a memory game that people take and,
what we're doing is trying to, to get
as many people as possible to take it.
Millions if we can.
And the goal is to try and find people
who have just naturally good memories.
Because, you know, people look at me and
I've, I've trained.
That's one thing,
but we really wanna look at people who
have this naturally, if that even exists.
If they don't,
that's also very enlightening.
So, one thing is to be playful and
childish and, and
try to tap into your inner memory.
The other thing is to
please participate in this,
we call it the Extreme Memory Challenge.
And people can log in.
It's extremememorychallenge.com.
And you'd be participating in a really,
great cause to hopefully end Alz,
Alzheimer's or and cognitive impairments.
>> Well, I so appreciate you taking
the time today to speak with us Nelson,
and I strongly, strongly encourage
all of our viewers to en,
enroll in the,
in the Extreme Memory Challenge.
I think it could be
a really an enhancement and
help a lot of researchers who are working
in a very, very important area.
So again,
my great thanks to you Nelson and
best of luck in your future,
future championships.
>> Thank you.
Thank you for having me.